Good evening.
Queen Victoria once said
"We are not interested in the possibilities of defeat;
it does not exist."
Queen Victoria would have loved Only Connect.
And like many of our viewers,
she would not have found these intros amusing.
Joining me for this quarter-final on my right:
Alexia Jarvis, who had her first cheese sandwich aged 30.
Jonathan Gibson, who can play Sweet Child o' Mine on the ukulele.
And their captain, Paddy Pamment...
...who has archived a hundred Charlton Athletic away match ticket stubs.
United by high balls and curveballs, they are the Pitchers.
Paddy, if I said "Surprise! We've changed the format...
...from the quarter-finals on, this is not a quiz but a talent contest,"
what would you do?
Oh my word. Um...
I have one thing in the back pocket
and that's a Michael McIntyre impression.
Either that or piano.
Well, we don't have a piano here. So...
If you were Michael McIntyre and I asked if you were looking forward to tonight's show,
you would say...?
Well, this is my favorite quiz show of them all, Victoria!
Thank you so much for having me, darling!
Hello, hello, hello!
That's really good!
That's a really good impression.
Very well done.
Well, the stakes are going to be high for your opponents, who are...
...on my left.
Raphael Kabo, who built his own lightsaber.
Carolina Cordero,
who dropped a clipboard into a hundred-year-old church organ.
And their captain, Emily Bourke...
...who failed to recognize Leonard Cohen in a Chinese restaurant.
Combined by conquering quests and characters, they are the Sorcerers.
Now, what about you, Emily? If this was suddenly...
...I'm not going to make you do an impression,
but if this was suddenly Britain's Got Talent...
...what would you pull out the bag?
I think it would be, yeah, either bassoon or singing.
What's your party piece? What would you play?
It's not interesting. There is a lovely Telemann sonata in F minor.
That absolutely IS interesting.
Some of our viewers are intellectuals, you know.
Not *you* obviously, but some people.
Lovely.
Nevertheless, we have not changed the format. We *are* going to play a quiz.
Pitchers, you won the toss, you'll be going first.
Please choose an Egyptian hieroglyph.
Uh, Eye of Horus, please.
Eye of Horus will be the first question of the game.
What do these clues have in common? Here's the first.
- It could be the same thing.
- Oh yeah.
- We'll need more though.
Next, please.
Directions of electromagnetic forces.
North or south? Polar or non-polar?
Maybe. But then what's the bread and drink? We need more, right?
Next, please.
Nine times table (first ten multiples).
Oh, it's what you do with your finger.
Are you sure you do it with your fingers?
Well yeah, I mean the reverse, yeah.
They're reverse... 'cause it's like 54, 45...
Do we want the last one?
Yeah, I think so.
Next, please.
Opposites.
Shall we say opposites?
Yeah, like mirrored...
These are opposites or mirrored images.
I think that might apply to some of them, but not all of the clues.
So that's not it. Sorcerers, you've got the chance of a bonus point.
There are hand rules for remembering these things.
They all feature in mnemonics involving the hands.
What clues can you tell me about?
So there's a, I think, a right-hand rule
for directions of electromagnetic forces?
Yes, that one's quite complicated to explain.
You make an L with your left hand, so that's how you know it's your left.
Left and right, like this.
And I don't know the other two.
The nine times table... I've forgotten how you do it,
but you do the entire nine times table on your fingers.
You can! So what you do... Starting on the left, and viewers...
...although I'm not good with left and right, but this is my left...
...you bend down the finger you want to multiply by nine.
So for example four. One, two, three, four. You bend that down.
And on one side you've got the tens and the other side the digits.
So one, two, three... 30. One, two, three, four, five, six... 36.
Is four times nine.
Oh, I love that.
And the bread and drink, you do that, and one is B and one is D.
Laying the table suddenly got a lot easier, didn't it?
Assuming we all do formal dining.
So you get the bonus point and what will your own question be?
Twisted Flax, please.
Twisted Flax.
A music question. What do they have in common? Here's the first.
[Music: I met Ezekiel Young from Salt Lake City about two years ago.]
[Music: And he told me he was single and we headed off right away...]
[Music: So we started living together.]
Next.
[Music: Oh no! You got it all wrong!]
[Music: I'm quick on the trigger with targets not much bigger than a pinpoint.
I'm number one.]
That's Annie Get Your Gun.
[Music: But my score with a feller is lower than a cellar.]
Next.
[Music: Will come out tomorrow. So you gotta hang on...]
[Music: ...to tomorrow.]
Are these musicals or songs with women's names in the title?
They are not.
So bonus chance for you now, Pitchers.
All sung by Annies.
They are all sung by Annies.
That last one, the musical "Annie". What was the third one?
That was "Annie Get Your Gun".
That's right, I think that must have been Doris Day singing that.
"Chicago" at clue one, and that's Annie who poisoned her husband.
And clue two...
...that's not a musical at all.
That's in fact the singer Annie with a single called "Chewing Gum".
What would you like, Pitchers, for your own question?
Uh, Two Reeds.
Two Reeds.
What connects these clues? Here's the first.
Rebus: learn new skills.
It's a type of cryptogram, isn't it, a rebus? Learn new skills.
It's also a detective.
That's true.
Next, please.
Resbus: hold back.
Sob... Sub... Su-bus... Going backwards?
We need more to puzzle it out, I think.
Yeah. Next, please.
Do we need to replace bus with something?
Oh yes. Reserve?
Relearn... Reserve...
Was it train?
If you change bus to train?
Retrain, restrain...
- Yeah.
- Yeah, bus to train.
Very good. Ah, I see.
Change bus to train and you
get these words and their definitions.
Exactly so.
It's a train replacement bus service.
Please talk me through the clues, what would those words be?
Retrain, to learn new skills, in clue one.
We have restrain, to hold back.
Contraindication.
That's clever, isn't it? Contrainedication.
And you didn't need to see "Untrained",
not having been taught particular skills.
Well done.
Sorcerers, what's next?
Water, please.
Water. These are gonna be picture clues.
What do they have in common? Here's the first.
A car crash. A serious accident.
Let's do next.
Next.
Tide? Tide pod?
A tab.
The tabs... Power...
Next.
That's The Edge. The Edge from U2.
A gauntlet.
Keys on a keyboard.
Not it.
Pitchers, another bonus chance.
Are these all lines?
I'm afraid not.
That first clue, it's a still from a TV program called "Collision".
We've got Collision, Powerball, The Edge of course, and Gauntlet.
They are games on Gladiators.
The reincarnated Gladiators show.
Pitchers, there's one choice left. What will it be?
The Lion, please Victoria.
Lion. What do these clues have in common? Here's the first.
Turkey? No, Austrian flag.
Vienna.
Is it capital?
Vienna... Queen of Africa...
Next, please.
Nigeria and outside?
Green... Green something...
Oh, is it Penguin?
It is... Like the Penguin book coloring?
African Penguin, Little Penguin... those are both penguins.
Is it just penguins?
You can bail me out if I get it wrong mate.
Penguins.
Um, in so far as African Penguin, Little Penguin,
and these are the color schemes for Penguin Books with those genres.
That is exactly right! And well done,
you get three points for coming in after two clues.
So that first series of Penguin books released...
Originally I think they were black and white...
...but they had a color block to show genre.
We are combining actual penguins with Penguin Books.
Sorcerers, one question left.
The Horned Viper.
What do these clues have in common? Here's the first.
Love perhaps...
Amazing?
Must be nothing.
Next.
Malted milk drink.
Ovaltine?
Horlicks?
Milo?
Next.
Tamagotchi or Neopets?
Tamagotchi.
Is there another virtual pet I don't know?
Next.
Oh, that's the... um...
...the Eames chair? No that's a different one.
Is it egg?
Are they all egg related?
Egg chair?
Related by eggs.
They are connected by eggs.
What can you tell me about the clues?
Love could be zero as in an... an egg?
That's right. People say that...
...love in tennis comes from "l'oeuf". We don't know that.
But one of the theories is that it's "l'oeuf",
but also of course that the zero resembles an egg.
What's that second clue?
Ovaltine... we don't know actually.
I mean Ovaltine's an oval.
Well, but it's Ovaltine because of the "ovo", the Latin for egg...
...combined with malt and the other ingredients.
What's the virtual pet?
Tamagotchi.
And "tamago" is the Japanese for egg.
It originally meant "egg watch" because it was a watch.
And the Arne Jacobsen chair, of course, the Egg Chair.
Well done.
That means at the end of Round One, the Sorcerers have 2 points...
...the Pitchers have 6.